<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>River&#39;s Blog</title>
  <subtitle>A blog about whatever technical stuff I feel like talking about today</subtitle>
  <link href="https://rseeber.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://rseeber.github.io/blog/" />
  <updated>2025-09-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://rseeber.github.io/blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name>River Seeber</name>
    <email>riverseeber12@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Isaac Asimov, Robots, AI, and Luddism</title>
    <link href="https://rseeber.github.io/blog/post/isaac-asimov-robots-ai-and-luddism/" />
    <updated>2025-09-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://rseeber.github.io/blog/post/isaac-asimov-robots-ai-and-luddism/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;September 24, 2025&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;introImg&quot; src=&quot;https://ia800402.us.archive.org/view_archive.php?archive=/12/items/olcovers662/olcovers662-L.zip&amp;file=6621014-L.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover for &#39;The Caves of Steel&#39;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just finished reading &lt;em&gt;The Caves of Steel&lt;/em&gt; (1953) by Isaac Asimov. I really enjoyed it. I guess it&#39;s a little weird to write a review for a 70 year old book, so instead I decided to put together whatever the hell this post is. We go over the book, but then also its implications on modern society, as well as draw-backs to the 19th century Luddite movement that occurred during the Industrial Revolution. Hope you enjoy, it&#39;s a little non-traditional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The plot&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this book was actually my first Asimov novel. The plot follows that of one Lije Baley, a detective who lives and works in the &lt;em&gt;heavily&lt;/em&gt; socially stratified big city of New York. The highly dense and compact nature of this city in the future means that most people don&#39;t have kitchens or bathrooms in their own houses or apartments, and must go to communal places for this. The entire city is encased in a dome, and shielded from the air and sunlight of the outside world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understandably, this unnatural way of living lends itself to some backlash movements. The Medievalists, as they&#39;re called, want a return to a time they refer to as the &amp;quot;Medieval&amp;quot; age. It becomes clear that what they mean by this is the 20th century or so, which to them is long, long past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This society is slowly being introduced to some very primitive robots — working in retail centers, and one in the detective office. All of them are quite dull, unable to perform advanced tasks. Even still, this represents a threat to the labor force, especially in a society such as this, where getting fired means decent from all of the comforts in life that you know, total abandonment at the bottom of society. (Are we sure this was written in the 1950s not the 2020s?) Anyways, this fear of unemployment creates a sense of Luddism within the minds of many Medievalists or even just regular folks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thetechbubble.substack.com/p/on-the-origins-of-dunes-butlerian&quot;&gt;https://thetechbubble.substack.com/p/on-the-origins-of-dunes-butlerian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of all this, the culture of Earth must tolerate some pompous, upper class society, called the &amp;quot;Spacers&amp;quot;, who live, you guessed it, up in space right above Earth. The Spacers are of high social standing, and tensions between the cultures are high, not least because of the push by the Spacers to introduce robots into the Earth culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is inside of this context that one of the Spacers are murdered within their own home in Spacetown. The Spacers expect it to be someone from Earth. They start up a joint investigation, with Lije Baley, an Earth man, being partnered up with R. Daneel Olivaw, a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; advanced robot from Spacetown. In fact, Daneel even passes for a human upon reasonably close inspection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investigation follows through looking into Medievalist secret societies, conspiracies, corruption, and Luddite aversion to automation technology which threatens the livelihood of the working class. By the end of the novel, Lije comes to change his view from that of a vague Medievalist, instead to believe in the cooperation between robots and humans, a transition to a so-called &amp;quot;C/Fe society&amp;quot; (Carbon-based life integrating with Iron-based life).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Luddism&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word Luddism is, of course, not actually used within the novel, but I mention it because I feel like the themes are overtly present in the Medievalist backlash to robots working positions once held by humans. In the real world, Luddites were a group of textile makers during the industrial revolution. They stood opposed to the &lt;em&gt;ways in which textile automation technology was being used&lt;/em&gt;. More specifically, the tools were being used to take power away from the textile workers, and it was outputting lower quality products for consumers than when it was all just made by hand. Luddites had no issue with the &lt;em&gt;idea&lt;/em&gt; of automation. What they didn&#39;t like was the way it was being used as a means by the owning upper-class to take away power from the poor working-class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In truth, Luddism and science fiction concern themselves with the same questions: not merely &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; the technology does, but who it does it &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; and who it does it &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; — Cory Doctorow, Locus Magazine&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://locusmag.com/feature/cory-doctorow-science-fiction-is-a-luddite-literature/&quot;&gt;https://locusmag.com/feature/cory-doctorow-science-fiction-is-a-luddite-literature/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even back in the 1950s, the awareness of where computers were headed was presently in the minds of many, who perhaps might have reason to worry about being replaced and laid off. In a certain capacity, those fears were justified, as the computer would become more and more advanced, and take a seat in various positions once ran by humans. Of course, at the same time, it brought in a whole new set of positions needing humans to fill. So life goes on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bringing in of the computer was in some ways used as a threat to workers, but for the most part, it was simply done out of pragmatism. Humans tend to be pretty bad at performing repetitive, pattern-based actions which do not require discretion. On the other hand, computers are pretty good at these kinds of activities. What computers &lt;em&gt;aren&#39;t&lt;/em&gt; good at is activities that require a certain level of situational context and discretion. Computers aren&#39;t good at determining whether or not you&#39;re returning this library book late for good reasons or not. They just know that its late. That&#39;s why we created self-checkout machines at the library, but still have a staff of librarians which can be a human to help you escape the strict rigidity of the computer bureaucracy. They can listen to you explain that your car broke down so you couldn&#39;t get it returned, and they can override the fees on your account, giving you amnesty. A computer is not suited towards that kind of task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, AI is being peddled as some kind of technology that attempts to replace humans in their everyday jobs. At the same time, AI is pretty bad at any task where it needs to &lt;em&gt;replace&lt;/em&gt; a human. Humans just perform too many small, discretionary decisions that current AI models are simply not possible of even realizing they should consider. The models just don&#39;t compare to the human mind if they&#39;re being made to try to &lt;em&gt;replace&lt;/em&gt; the human mind. That&#39;s not what this tool is ever going to do, not in the near future anyways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But AI is not useless. AI has potential for &lt;em&gt;assisting&lt;/em&gt; humans, when it&#39;s done organically. When your boss fires half your department, but tells you that you need to offset the workload onto &amp;quot;AI integrations&amp;quot; or something like that, the AI is going to perform badly. The department is going to put out shit content compared to what they used to. On the other hand, when you just have a thing you need to do, and you realize that an AI can make a template for this thoughtless task to help speed it up, that&#39;s a genuine boost. But those boosts are, much to the chagrin of the employer class, not actually that dramatic, and definitely don&#39;t create the kind of productivity boosts that allow you to fire half of every department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his blog, Cory Doctorow often explores the ideas of &amp;quot;Centaurs&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Reverse-Centaurs&amp;quot; when it comes to automation technology. A centaur is a person who, in the natural course of their duties, finds a productive way to use the automation technology to offload some of their own work, making them more productive at the job they&#39;ve always been doing. It lets them get more done, but at the end of the day, they are free to use the automation tool where they feel it is appropriate, and abandon it in instances where it is not useful or needed. They are given control and discretion over its use. A centaur is a human standing atop a robot body which they can control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pluralistic.net/2025/09/11/vulgar-thatcherism/&quot;&gt;https://pluralistic.net/2025/09/11/vulgar-thatcherism/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A reverse-centaur, on the other hand, is a squishy human being piloted and controlled &lt;em&gt;by the robot!&lt;/em&gt; The reverse-centaur is a worker whose boss just fired a bunch of their coworkers, and expects them to pick up the slack by using AI. When the quality of the work goes down, the boss will either not care, or, worse still, they might blame the remaining workers for being so careless, despite the ludicrously cramped deadlines and under-staffing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Weren&#39;t we supposed to be talking about Isaac Asimov?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right. Back to the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s important to remember that the conclusion of the book involved an acceptance that &lt;em&gt;humans need to learn to cooperate with robots&lt;/em&gt;. In the backdrop of the 1950s, it might be easy to mistake calls for robot integration with that of racial integration that were going on at the time. This was my initial viewpoint of the themes of the so-called &amp;quot;C/Fe culture&amp;quot; that the pro-robot faction was calling for. Upon further inspection, it becomes clear that this is not the true nature of things, and the comparison really isn&#39;t fair. These robots &lt;em&gt;do not form a culture of their own&lt;/em&gt;. The robots are not sentient, and they do not pretend to be. The robots are machines, and do not have desires of their own, besides in how they seek to serve humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this, the characters in the book often saw the &amp;quot;C/Fe culture&amp;quot; stuff as being a cultural mixing, notably the Medievalists and others of the anti-robot factions. They feared that these newfangled robots would demand to fill human jobs and be treated with humanity. All this on top of their utter superiority at performing certain kinds of tasks that humans could never hope to achieve (think: basically anything a computer can do better than a human, but then give that computer opposable thumbs and a body to walk around in).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the mistaken way that the Earth society looks at robots in. They see them as a threat, as some kind of culture of their own. Oftentimes within the book, Daneel Olivaw — the advanced robot from Spacetown — would shock the humans around him by his utter lack of care for human prejudice against robots. He is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; sentient. He does not have feelings to hurt. When Lije Baley admitted that he was prejudiced against robots, Daneel said it didn&#39;t matter, so long as they could work together effectively. The robot had no sense of cultural identity that needed to be defended from trampling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one point, a Medievalist radical took a swing against Daneel. The robot didn&#39;t see it coming, but did his best to back away to soften the blow — not to himself, but to protect the hand of the attacker from being hurt by his metal frame. He didn&#39;t care that he was being attacked, he just needed to follow the First Law of Robotics: to protect the human.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At other times, people would express hatred towards the more primitive robots in front of Daneel, then apologize, as if they had offended him. He told them he didn&#39;t care, he couldn&#39;t be offended even if he tried — he&#39;s a robot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What does this tell us about automation and technology?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is that technology does not &lt;em&gt;inherently&lt;/em&gt; threaten humanity. It simply doesn&#39;t. Technology is created by humans, in order to best suit humans. Within this story, we are to believe that the people who create and distribute the robots (Spacetown) genuinely hold the best interests of the Earthmen in mind when creating their robots. This is the premise upon which the acceptance of all of this lies. This suits the story well, though it would incorrect to say that it is the only way it could have been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If, for instance, the story took place in a society that had a fairly strong working class, and which the owning class wanted to assert their dominance by breaking up unions, firing workers for expressing discontent with their conditions, and otherwise just putting down the labor force, the story might be different. It might then be more plausible to say that the owning class is pushing robots down on society in order to take away agency from the working class. In that case, the argument that &amp;quot;by just simply cooperating with the robots, humanity (and the working class) can be better off&amp;quot; would fall flat. You cannot cooperate with a technology that was expressly designed to destroy you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is where we stand in our real world in the year 2025. We must ask ourselves who it is that is designing these so-called &amp;quot;Artificial Intelligence&amp;quot; tools? Are they people who have the best interests of regular people, or are they designed by corporate tech monopolies, which have demonstrated time and time again that they will sacrifice the well-being of countless workers in order to further their power, wealth, and influence?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AI technologies we are being fed at current time are created by money-hungry monopolists who would love nothing more than to have us all at their mercy. They are forced upon us (often, but not always) by bosses who want to speed up our work speed, while sacrificing both output quality and our own well-being, just in the name of increased profits. This has the result of decreasing quality of life for both consumers and employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it doesn&#39;t have to be this way, not inherently. What we are witnessing is a result of our economic system, not a result of the technology itself. The extreme stratification of our economic environment is what leads all of this. AI models are massive and bulky, and are pretty damn difficult to run on cheap hardware, but as the economic incentives begin to make corporations try to get AI models to run on consumer hardware (be it out of the chase of the AI bubble, or simply a desire to get AI spyware running on everybody&#39;s smartphone), we&#39;re seeing models pop up that are actually reasonably competent that can run on low specs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we absolutely &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; right now, is for more of these reasonably sized tools to keep coming out. Open source models, runnable by anybody. Tools that aren&#39;t being gatekept behind a singular service provider, who can refuse access for particular uses it deems inappropriate. We&#39;ve got a decent amount of tools like this, but it&#39;s limited. To be fair, the actual utility of AI in general is limited. But still, the idea that this technology keeps coming out and we&#39;re all just going to be better off for it all, even though it&#39;s all held up and controlled by our corporate overlords is ridiculous. If this is going to be a Good Technology, then it&#39;s going to need to be a technology that People Actually Own, not one that they rent access to, one prompt at a time. Even better than that would be if it were being &lt;em&gt;designed&lt;/em&gt; by people who have a shared interest in the collective well-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I genuinely think that Machine Learning (it&#39;s not actually AI, btw, that would require a level of &#39;intelligence&#39;) has a lot of real potential, especially the LLMs. It&#39;s just that everybody has got their heads so far up their own asses about whatever the hell the AI bros &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; that it&#39;s going to revolutionize, that they can&#39;t see the potential of what it might &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; be able to do if we just stopped fantasizing about firing everyone for just 10 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Wrap up&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, not exactly a traditional book review post, but I feel like I covered all the important parts. Major themes, general plot, implied conclusions about technology, and also the way we can turn the text to a modern interpretation. I hope yall enjoyed this less-than-traditional post from me. I enjoyed reading this book, and looking at the way that robots were thought of &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; the major advent of the computer was interesting, in comparison to how we think of them now within pop culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Check this out&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Some links after the blog&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pluralistic: &lt;em&gt;It&#39;s still censorship (even if it doesn&#39;t violate the First Amendment)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://pluralistic.net/2025/09/22/one-throat-to-choke/&quot;&gt;https://pluralistic.net/2025/09/22/one-throat-to-choke/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More Perfect Union: &lt;em&gt;I Took Bernie Into Deep Trump Country. Can He Win Them Over?&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RP8Oxe6OxJc&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RP8Oxe6OxJc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Snopes: &lt;em&gt;DOJ removed study from website showing most domestic terrorism is right-wing&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.snopes.com/fact-check/doj-removes-study-website/&quot;&gt;https://www.snopes.com/fact-check/doj-removes-study-website/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The study in question:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;What NIJ Research Tells Us About Domestic Terrorism&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20250911165140/https://www.ojp.gov/pdffiles1/nij/306123.pdf&quot;&gt;https://web.archive.org/web/20250911165140/https://www.ojp.gov/pdffiles1/nij/306123.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vox: &lt;em&gt;Why obvious lies make great propaganda&lt;/em&gt; (2018) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nknYtlOvaQ0&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nknYtlOvaQ0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Happy Constitution Day</title>
    <link href="https://rseeber.github.io/blog/post/happy-constitution-day/" />
    <updated>2025-09-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://rseeber.github.io/blog/post/happy-constitution-day/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;September 17, 2025&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Constitution Day to everyone living in the United States! On this day, September 17, all the way back in 1787, the final draft of the US Constitution was signed, and would slowly make its way to the Congress of the Confederation, being ratified by the 13 states a year later, replacing the Articles of the Confederation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way, if you&#39;ve never the Constitution in full, or you haven&#39;t done it recently, I highly recommend you take today as an excuse to do so. It&#39;s fairly short, and can be easily read in a single sitting. It&#39;s one of the most important documents that relates to our current legal system in the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20240930125328/https://constitution.congress.gov/constitution/&quot;&gt;https://web.archive.org/web/20240930125328/https://constitution.congress.gov/constitution/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During deliberation over whether the US should accept this new constitution or not, there were 2 factions that emerged on the issue. The Federalists, who promoted the constitution (which enacted a &amp;quot;federalist&amp;quot; system of governance), and the less creatively named Anti-Federalists, who were weary of potential structural dangers that might come associated with this new system. In order to quell some of the fears by the Anti-Federalists of authoritarian rule and the trampling of civil liberties, Congress passed the Bill of Rights — 10 amendments, codifying certain basic liberties as constitutional rights. The Federalists felt as though this was unnecessary, claiming instead that the &lt;em&gt;structure&lt;/em&gt; of the Constitution itself serves as a bill of rights. In Federalist 84, Alexander Hamilton wrote this on the subject:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the proposed Constitution, if adopted, will be the bill of rights of the Union. Is it one object of a bill of rights to declare and specify the political privileges of the citizens in the structure and administration of the government? This is done in the most ample and precise manner in the plan of the convention; comprehending various precautions for the public security, which are not to be found in any of the State constitutions. Is another object of a bill of rights to define certain immunities and modes of proceeding, which are relative to personal and private concerns? This we have seen has also been attended to, in a variety of cases, in the same plan. Adverting therefore to the substantial meaning of a bill of rights, it is absurd to allege that it is not to be found in the work of the convention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gutenberg.org/files/1404/1404-h/1404-h.htm#link2H_4_0084&quot;&gt;https://www.gutenberg.org/files/1404/1404-h/1404-h.htm#link2H_4_0084&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamilton was right in some ways. He&#39;s saying that the Constitution dictates how the government can operate. The government is to be a body composed of publicly elected and liable individuals consisting of varying constituencies from one representative to another. On top of that, it was specifically engineered to create contradictions of power between the different bodies of government, so as to prevent any individual body becoming too over-zealous with power. It creates limitations on which bodies, if any, can conduct certain types of actions. It bans certain actions altogether, such as retroactive application of laws (called &#39;ex post facto laws&#39;), while at the same time guaranteeing certain rights to citizens, such as the right to trial, (called the right to a &#39;writ of habeas corpus&#39;). It is a system that has been engineered to prevent tyrannical takeover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to go over that point again, because I think it&#39;s important. &lt;strong&gt;Our government was designed, in our Constitution, to prevent wannabe tyrants and dictators from trampling over the people, and to prevent them from seizing too much power.&lt;/strong&gt; Our Constitution was designed with an adversarial threat model for its own leaders. The way the Founders saw it, one of the biggest threats to The United States was our own elected representatives. They designed an entire system, explicitly in order to prevent those representatives — Congressmen, Judges, &lt;em&gt;Presidents&lt;/em&gt; — from becoming too powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Testing Our Efforts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, our country is getting a real life test of those safety measures. We&#39;re only 9 months into the second presidency of Donald Trump, and he&#39;s already ran through a number of structural barriers that have never before been circumvented. Structural barriers considered to be load bearing supports for a functioning democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He&#39;s suspended the right to trial for suspected immigrants, making it impossible for a legal citizen to prove that they are not, in fact, the immigrant that ICE thinks them to be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deportation_of_Kilmar_Abrego_Garcia&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deportation_of_Kilmar_Abrego_Garcia&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He&#39;s ignored court orders from judges because he didn&#39;t like their rulings, and had to be fought hand over fist to actually obey them finally:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apnews.com/article/aclu-trump-deportations-el-salvador-boasberg-e447c61de031150669d01687edc4b11b&quot;&gt;https://apnews.com/article/aclu-trump-deportations-el-salvador-boasberg-e447c61de031150669d01687edc4b11b&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He&#39;s been found to have illegally deployed National Guard troops on Los Angeles, with public plans to deploy on other big US cities (more specifically, big cities whose local politics swing left-wing or anti-Trump):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apnews.com/article/trump-newsom-los-angeles-national-guard-d6c8450a3ac2de34e669ef0836d22cbc&quot;&gt;https://apnews.com/article/trump-newsom-los-angeles-national-guard-d6c8450a3ac2de34e669ef0836d22cbc&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He&#39;s fired certain public officials even when Congress has passed explicit laws insulating them from being fired by the President, such as members of the NLRB. He&#39;s discussing doing the same for members on The Federal Reserve, despite there being laws preventing such thing unless there is good cause to remove (not just partisan disagreement).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2025/01/28/nx-s1-5277103/nlrb-trump-wilcox-abruzzo-democrats-labor&quot;&gt;https://www.npr.org/2025/01/28/nx-s1-5277103/nlrb-trump-wilcox-abruzzo-democrats-labor&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Power of the Pen&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the more abstract, his slew of Executive Orders in the first months of his second presidency have been very explicitly clear grasps by the president for legislative power. The reason why this in particular is worrying is that the Executive and Legislative branches are setup in very structurally different ways, so as to create two very different modes of operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d like to draw once again upon The Federalist Papers, this time Federalist 70, another one of Hamilton&#39;s:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the legislature, promptitude of decision is oftener an evil than a benefit. The differences of opinion, and the jarrings of parties in that department of the government, though they may sometimes obstruct salutary plans, yet often promote deliberation and circumspection, and serve to check excesses in the majority. When a resolution too is once taken, the opposition must be at an end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What he&#39;s describing here is the inherent &lt;em&gt;innefficiency&lt;/em&gt; of Congress. That inefficiency is the point. We shouldn&#39;t be passing laws in a &amp;quot;move fast and break things&amp;quot; kind of way. Laws are universally applicable, and if passed without much consideration, could have disastrous ramifications for all kinds of people. The great innovation of our legislative system in the United States is that it is so darn easy to prevent a &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; bill from getting passed. This way, disadvantaged minorities can leverage that ability to stop the bill in order to force the majority to add concessions to the bill before you allow it to go through and become law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all of this fighting, a great amount of thinking about the bill must occur, and it will continuously go through various improvements, shedding off bad provisions, and perhaps even gaining new good ones that couldn&#39;t have been imagined until it came to the debate floor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, once the bill has passed, Hamilton notes that it must be enforced without this same level of deep introspection. The law is the law, and once we&#39;ve slowly decided what the law is, we must now move to &lt;em&gt;quickly&lt;/em&gt; enforce it with haste and vigor. Thus, he argues, the Executive branch must have much energy. This forms the basis for the Framer&#39;s argument to have a single person at the head of the Executive branch — The President.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, all of this talk about energy in the Executive might seem to support everything Trump is doing in all his vigorous actions as President. The Framers never argued against an energetic Presidency, so this is in line with their vision of America, surely?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue is that Donald Trump is not just merely applying the laws that Congress has passed in an energetic manner. If he were simply executing the resolutions which had already gone through intense debate and compromise before becoming law, then the vigor would be appreciated. But Donald Trump is largely creating his own new plans for this country entirely independent of Congress or that deliberatory process. In many cases, as already stated, he is going directly &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; policies mandated by Congress. What we are witnessing is not &#39;Energy in the Executive&#39;, but rather, &lt;em&gt;legislative energy&lt;/em&gt;, which just so happens to originate from the Executive branch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Is This What America Needs Right Now?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s an argument going around right now that our country needs all of this. That we need somebody like Trump to come in, destroying and subverting all limitations on his power, in order to actually accomplish important change in our country which has been tied up in governmental gridlock for the past 2 decades. Then, at the end of his 4 years, he&#39;s going to be all done with his title of supreme leader, and he&#39;s going to leave. Then, when the next President is elected, they&#39;ll just never be able to pull the same power plays as Trump, because apparently it&#39;s only possible for Trump to do it, and nobody else is charismatic enough to repeat the process after he&#39;s already set the precedent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea that &amp;quot;Too Much Democracy is hindering America, and is at the root of all our problems&amp;quot; is a common idea in the minds of a lot of Conservatives right now. Not to say that they &lt;em&gt;don&#39;t&lt;/em&gt; believe in Democracy, it&#39;s just that I&#39;ve personally seen a lot of complaining about &amp;quot;too much red tape in the system&amp;quot; coming from that side of the aisle. I mean, that&#39;s kind of what the whole DOGE project with Elon Musk was about. But it&#39;s also an underscore of the entire way Trump 2.0 is behaving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a recent turn of events for Conservatives. Traditionally, Conservatives have believed strongly in the core mission of the Constitution, or at least if they didn&#39;t, they pretended to. Back in 2011, Supreme Court Justice Antonin Scalia — a &lt;em&gt;famous&lt;/em&gt; Conservative justice who was appointed by none other than Ronald Reagan — sat before the Senate to talk about the role of Judiciary in today&#39;s world. He spoke about the way that the US is uniquely set up to &lt;em&gt;contradict power&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ggz_gd--UO0&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ggz_gd--UO0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the United States, a bill must pass before &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; legislative bodies, with the same wording, before it is allowed to become a law. Those two bodies are elected in &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different manners. Then it is passed to the President, who can veto it if he doesn&#39;t like it. Again, the President is elected in a very different manner than either legislative house. There could be immense ideological disagreement between all 3 of them. Scalia explains that to people living in Europe, and sometimes even those within the United States, this entire system seems to amount to nothing more than a big machine that creates endless gridlock. That we can&#39;t get anything done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He says that&#39;s the wrong way to look at it. That we&#39;re supposed to love the gridlock. The gridlock is the point. He&#39;s echoing the same point that Hamilton was making in Federalist 70 where he wrote about the deliberation that was supposed to occur in Congress before a bill could get passed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scalia was a &lt;em&gt;staunch&lt;/em&gt; Conservative. And his beliefs on this topic are part of what made him a &lt;em&gt;hero&lt;/em&gt; to the Conservative side of politics. What I&#39;m trying to demonstrate here is that there&#39;s nothing inherently Conservative about believing that we need to brush through this whole system of &lt;em&gt;intentionally engineered friction&lt;/em&gt; and lather it in lubrication in order to expedite the process. We do not want the process to be systemically expedited. We want the laws of this land to have been passed before the great machine of debate and deliberation that is our Legislative process. And so if these ideas are not inherent to Conservatism, then I&#39;ve shown that I&#39;m not attacking Trump for being Conservative, or rapidly instituting Conservative policy. I may dislike those things, but it is what it is. What I&#39;m criticizing him for here — and in the strongest way I know how — is for subverting America&#39;s founding principles of contradiction of powers, of checks and balances, of everything that the drafters of the Constitution were fighting for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;He Fancies Himself a King&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump has decided that his preferred method of governing in this country is to ignore laws passed by Congress, and when Congress has decided not to act in a particular area (perhaps because their deliberation has led them to the conclusion that it would be improper to do so), he finds ways to inaccurately interpret laws that were never meant to serve for those purposes in order to create a legal basis to enforce his private policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His basis for trying to invade US cities with the National Guard are prime examples. No law allows him to do this, except for if he claims there to be some kind of national &amp;quot;crime emergency&amp;quot; going on in these cities, a fact that is simply not true. He&#39;s also used a similarly faulty basis in how he&#39;s announced there to be a &amp;quot;foreign invasion of immigrants&amp;quot; into this country, which is the basis for which he is suspending the right to a fair trial before being deported. Without this trial, there is no way for legitimate citizens to prove that they are in this country legally. If you don&#39;t give immigrants a right to a trial before deporting them, it means you&#39;re fine deporting US citizens without a trial, since they will have no basis upon which they can prove their legal status if they&#39;re denied a court trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact of the matter is that our President is governing by creating his own legislation. That is the way that kings of old ran their kingdoms. That&#39;s not how Democracies run, and it&#39;s definitely not how The United States of America runs. We do not have kings in this country, but it seems that our President disagrees with that fact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re in a very scary place right now. I don&#39;t want to minimize the threat, but I&#39;d like to point out the fact that this is the one thing that this country was designed for. We&#39;re seeing a lot of fights right now legally against the president. Culturally, every time Trump gets held up for breaking the law, he decries it as a moment of a &amp;quot;rouge judge&amp;quot; trying to be a dictator over him. So he simply refuses to accept the role of checks and balances, so he tries to delegitimize it. He&#39;s ignoring and going against large portions of the law right now, but it&#39;s important to remember that he&#39;s still being held up. Courts are finding his actions to be illegal and forcing him to stop. There are still moments where Trump does not ultimately prevail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just this month, a federal judge found that Trump&#39;s use of the California National Guard in Los Angeles was illegal. This is of course coming after most of the damage has already been done, but the ruling sets a useful precedent that this kind of thing will not be allowed to happen in other cities, such as Chicago, which the President has boldly asserted that he will be sending troops to at some undisclosed point in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thehill.com/regulation/court-battles/5481178-judge-rules-trumps-use-of-us-military-in-la-was-illegal/&quot;&gt;https://thehill.com/regulation/court-battles/5481178-judge-rules-trumps-use-of-us-military-in-la-was-illegal/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People are fighting back against the administration, and some of them are actually winning some ground, even if it is an entirely unfair uphill fight against authoritarianism. The point is that as terrible of a predicament our country is in right now, &lt;em&gt;we are not helpless!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I want to urge people to realize that the words coming out of Trump and his supporters mouths are explicitly &lt;em&gt;anti-American and unpatriotic&lt;/em&gt;. To break so many of the institutional limits within our Constitution, to decry the concept of checks and balances, it is to spit in the face of our founders and the American promise of freedom. The MAGA party loves to call themselves patriots, and to criticize Trump&#39;s opponents on supposed unpatriotic grounds. But the issue is that MAGA stands for values that are antithetical to America and our values laid out in the Constitution. Donald Trump thinks that anyone who stops him from assuming complete and utter control of the government is a rogue agent scheming to become their own dictator. Donald Trump believes that anybody in power who stops him from carrying out his illegal plans has overstepped their bounds. Donald Trump believes that he is entitled to do anything he wants. If you agree with him, you do not believe in America. I&#39;m tired of pretending that the MAGA faction that is destroying the infrastructure of checks and balances in this country &lt;em&gt;isn&#39;t&lt;/em&gt; un-American.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Fighting Back&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re a concerned citizen who is scared of the way Trump is proceeding, might I perhaps persuade you to &lt;em&gt;do something about it!&lt;/em&gt; If you feel like Trump has massively overstepped his bounds as President, I can&#39;t urge you enough, &lt;em&gt;please&lt;/em&gt;, we need to go out and get organized! So, what on Earth can we do to stop this man from tearing up our Democracy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;No Kings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you remember the &#39;No Kings&#39; protests that took place all across the country in June earlier this year to protest Trump, you might like to know that another day of protest has been planned, this time falling on October 18. If you&#39;re tired of President Trump acting as a dictator, you should go to this event. There are so many of these going on across the country. Even in my small, relatively Conservative town within California, there&#39;s a local event, so I don&#39;t have to drive to a big city to partake. You can check out different locations on the map they provide on their website:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nokings.org/#map&quot;&gt;https://www.nokings.org/#map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do go, one thing I must urge you to do is to represent an energy of peace. In addition, don&#39;t allow them to label you as insurrectionists who hate America. We do not hate America. We love America, and we&#39;re showing up to this event because of that. We&#39;re showing up to protest Donald Trump because his actions ring in contradiction of this country&#39;s founding principles. We say No Kings because we believe that Donald Trump represents everything that this country is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bring American flags, bring printouts of the Constitution, The Federalist Papers, the Declaration of Independence. Don&#39;t burn flags, don&#39;t hang them upside down. Even if your intentions are patriotic or pro-American, that&#39;s not how it gets interpreted when those who disagree with you see it on social media. Do your best to represent what the anti-Trump faction really is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Call Your Representatives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know you&#39;ve heard this a million times before, but I&#39;m serious, call them. You can send emails too, though I&#39;ve heard that phone calls tend to be more effective. Pressure them to take action against Trump. Pressure them to speak out publicly on an issue that they&#39;re neglecting, even if the Conservative majority in Congress prevents them exerting much direct power against the administration. If your representatives are Conservative, &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; make a point to call them. Tell them that their support of Trump&#39;s undemocratic actions makes you lose faith in them. Tell them you want them to stop standing in line behind a man who hates this country. Tell them your vote is only cast for people who love this country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve never called your representatives before, it&#39;s super easy. Here&#39;s a really good video tutorial on how to do it, if you&#39;re nervous. Don&#39;t worry, your representatives aren&#39;t going to be the ones picking up the phone, it&#39;ll just be an office secretary who takes down your information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GX_ERS7U_WQ&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GX_ERS7U_WQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Vote&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a little preemptive, but it&#39;s important. The November 2026 Congressional election is going to be crucial if we want to stop some of the worse effects of the Trump takeover. It&#39;s common for there to be a blue wave in midterms during Republican presidencies, and vice versa. At the same time, there&#39;s an ongoing effort, initiated by Trump, to get red states like Texas to Gerrymander their district map outside of a census year, in order to squeeze out some extra Republican seats in the House. There&#39;s talk about a counter effort being taken on by various blue states, including California, but in either case, the vote for Congress incredibly important this midterm. If you want Congress to be able to actually fight back against this takeover, having a Democratic majority is going to be vitally important, since we know at this point that Republicans will only ever comply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recommend making sure that you&#39;re registered to vote, even if you&#39;ve registered already. Databases can become corrupted, and you might need to register again. You also might need to update some information like your address or vote-by-mail preferences. You can check your registration in just a few easy clicks here. Just click &#39;Voter Registration Status&#39;, select your state, and it will take you to your state&#39;s voter registration website. If you&#39;d like to register, click &#39;Register To Vote,&#39; and proceed in the same manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nass.org/can-I-vote&quot;&gt;https://www.nass.org/can-I-vote&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might not love Democrats, I sure as hell don&#39;t, but don&#39;t let that stop you from voting against a Republican who is only ever going to bend the knee to Trump. Vote for somebody who is not happy with the way things are going on right now in DC. Be a single-issue voter, where that issue is the maintenance of Democracy and our Constitution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Check this out&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some links after the blog&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AP News: &lt;em&gt;Tracking the lawsuits against the Trump administration&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://apnews.com/projects/trump-executive-order-lawsuit-tracker/&quot;&gt;https://apnews.com/projects/trump-executive-order-lawsuit-tracker/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On Not Surrendering in Advance (Or At Any Point Thereafter)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meditationsinanemergency.com/on-not-surrendering-in-advance-or-during-or-at-any-point-thereafter/&quot;&gt;https://www.meditationsinanemergency.com/on-not-surrendering-in-advance-or-during-or-at-any-point-thereafter/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Atlantic: &lt;em&gt;Apologies: You Have Reached the End of Your Free-Trial Period of America!&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/newsletters/archive/2025/09/america-free-trial-services/684072/?gift=jQN1t1D1nkO2TQodBiz5KLmz9qdi35_pconlf7F6jjg&quot;&gt;https://www.theatlantic.com/newsletters/archive/2025/09/america-free-trial-services/684072/?gift=jQN1t1D1nkO2TQodBiz5KLmz9qdi35_pconlf7F6jjg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A notional design studio.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://ethanmarcotte.com/wrote/a-notional-design-studio/&quot;&gt;https://ethanmarcotte.com/wrote/a-notional-design-studio/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Web Was Designed to Be Open</title>
    <link href="https://rseeber.github.io/blog/post/the-web-was-designed-to-be-open/" />
    <updated>2025-08-11T02:25:20Z</updated>
    <id>https://rseeber.github.io/blog/post/the-web-was-designed-to-be-open/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;July 13, 2025&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Free and Open Web&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internet is a truly incredible thing. Founded on the principle of shared ownership, the internet does not belong to any one group or person, it is shared by all of us. There is no single group you must go through in order to access the internet, nor in order to host an online service. There is no single set of rules governing what is and is not allowed to be posted on the internet. The internet deters censorship because new sovereign territory can be created online simply by hosting a server. With that server, you are created a new space on the internet, a new node added to the network. Within that node, you are free to do anything you like, so long as it is legal in the country you&#39;re hosting it in -- otherwise you might get some knocks on your door IRL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internet being this way means that it cannot be controlled, truncated, censored, or destroyed by any overzealous entities -- be they politicians, tech corporations, or otherwise anyone else with the power to attempt a move like that. The internet remains strong, unfettered by the whims of would-be autocrats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrast this model with the model we use for many of the online serves common throughout our society. Social Media is almost universally done using a centralized model. You use some service, say Facebook for example. You download an app provided to you by the Facebook corporation. When you want to post your social content online, you upload it through that app up to the Facebook servers. No new or sovereign land is created in this process, all media is retained on the already existing Facebook node. There is no way to host a new node, and let the content on that node be visible as regular Facebook content through the app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you wanted to host a new server, some piece of sovereign territory upon the web. You would be free to do so, but your content would not show up on the Facebook network. Users would have to leave the Facebook app in order to view your content. There would be no way to view both Facebook content and your content using the same app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Free and Open Social Net?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it doesn&#39;t have to be this way. What if we created a social media that worked the same way that the web does? Where the social network consists of distinct nodes controlled and operated by separate people? Those people could each set the rules of what is and is not allowed to exist on their node -- rather than having all content moderation be mandated by a single controlling authority like Facebook? Much like the web, we could create open standards for this technology. That way, anyone can create a program that can view this content. For the web, we called it Web Browsers, for social media, it will be a Social Media Client. A developer will have access to the standard, and will be free to implement any additional features, or organize the app in any way they see fit. We will not be bound and stuck with the design decisions of a single corporation. Users with different tastes will be enabled to cater to their own preferences for visual design of the interface that they want to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people reading this who have been in tech and hacker spaces long enough may be thinking right now of the decentralized alternatives to corporate social media. Mastodon and Bluesky both come to mind as possible contenders. For Bluesky, I will be brief and say that it is 1) not ready yet as a developed platform, and 2) it is not making enough significant strides for true decentralization. If Bluesky were to disappear from the internet tomorrow, there would not be a feasible way for the rest of the community to continue hosting the network without updating the protocol first.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://tormentnexus.substack.com/i/152261629/a-protocol-not-a-platform&quot;&gt;https://tormentnexus.substack.com/i/152261629/a-protocol-not-a-platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
As for Mastodon, while it is a truly decentralized network that can be entirely run without the help of any centralized authority, the underlying ActivityPub protocol that it relies on is both complicated and confusing, as well as overly vague, leaving many important questions unanswered in the specification, leading to much confusion for developers. The protocol is perhaps a good basis on which to build an actually concrete protocol, but in my own honest opinion, it is overly complicated, and a drain of the valuable time and resources of an open source community of intelligent developers. 
&lt;p&gt;Dennis Schubert, a project manager for the Diaspora* project -- another attempt at a social media network, although much smaller that both Bluesky or ActivityPub -- wrote a pretty good article on the issues with the ActivityPub protocol. In that article, he also lays out some of the bigger flaws in the existing Diaspora* project that make it also unsuitable in many ways, but I&#39;ll leave that to you to look into.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://overengineer.dev/blog/2019/01/13/activitypub-final-thoughts-one-year-later/&quot;&gt;https://overengineer.dev/blog/2019/01/13/activitypub-final-thoughts-one-year-later/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Clean, Simple Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I propose a simpler way of doing things. I&#39;m not going to put forward a concrete protocol, as I&#39;m only just starting to work on these ideas myself, but I&#39;d like to lay down the groundwork for what I think should someday become a solid protocol. The so-called &amp;quot;UNIX design principles&amp;quot; promote simplicity and modularity in all things that you create. Each module of your project should do one thing, and do that one thing well. Further modules can be appended to the overall project in order to create a program (or protocol, in our case) that can do many things. Our new protocol would work something like this. You may ignore the more specific details of this description in favor of the general principles I&#39;m trying to isolate in how I create this example. The point is simplicity, which we will achieve through modularity.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix_philosophy&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix_philosophy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
You would have two sides to the network. There would be clients, AKA &quot;users&quot;, and then there are the servers, which host the content for the users. A user would be free to host their content in any number of ways. It would be a very similar experience to that of hosting a web server. You are free to host it yourself if you know how to, or you may turn to any number of middle men who will do it for you. In the world of the web, this would be services like Wordpress, Medium, NeoCities, GitHub Pages, etc. Unlike ActivityPub, very little server-to-server interaction would occur, if any. When you as a user want to look at a post by your friend, your client software would request the content directly from their server. If you want to interact with that content (commenting, liking, etc), that interaction would be sent to and stored directly on the server where the original post is stored. The post would not be shared around with other servers like it does in the ActivityPub protocol. This is done to simplify things, and reduce scaling difficulties.
&lt;p&gt;As for the design of the clients, and the specific toolings used, feed content would be generated as an RSS feed for each user. So if you are following 5 friends, your client would fetch 5 RSS feeds at refresh time, looking for any posts inside of those 5 feeds that you have not yet seen, and then putting it on your timeline. Content itself would likely be stored as HTML or XML, or something of the sort. The benefit being that we do not need to teach the client software how to handle all 48 thousand content types, from image posts, to videos, to microblogs, to audio notes, to story posts. Instead, we could just encode the content using an extensible format like html or xml that support embedding tags for any content type imaginable. If you want to do an image post, your client software will simply embed an &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;img&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag into the post. For microblogging, it will put text inside of the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag. Use a format like html and you can encode anything you desire, even things which the designers of this future protocol couldn&#39;t have imagined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea here is that we&#39;re re-using existing protocols and tools. This lets us re-use technologies for understanding those protocols. Web apps already know how to render HTML, we can simply use the existing engine for reading it. There are plenty of libraries around for reading RSS and XML feeds as machine readable data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In keeping with this idea, we would also want to create some kind of direct messaging service within the standard, for when users would like to communicate with one another. Perhaps we could use a protocol like XMPP or something similar. The fantastic benefit of this is that smaller servers which don&#39;t want to handle storing direct messages could offshore their implementation of XMPP to another server that they simply point to in their metadata file for the user. Perhaps a server might have a user called Alice. She has an account on this server at &lt;code&gt;https://example.com/alice&lt;/code&gt;, but the metadata file (perhaps &lt;code&gt;https://example.com/alice/index.xml&lt;/code&gt;), lists that her messaging endpoint is at &lt;code&gt;https://external-server.net/alice&lt;/code&gt;. Thus, when a user wants to message Alice, they will send an XMPP message directly to Alice at that endpoint on a separate server. Perhaps our example server would even handle the user credentials for the external server, making sure login details always match with the main server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should they wish, a user would even be free to hand pick the XMPP server they want to use. Maybe they could do so in order to reduce the number of message inboxes they have, so they can re-use an already existing account to use for their social media DMs as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Closing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps some of the specific recommendations for the protocol wouldn&#39;t be perfect. A lot more thinking needs to go into this kind of thing. But as it stands right now, we are very dry on alternatives to the corporate social media platforms that are seen by many as the only real choice available. Creating social media in a way that mimics the shape of the free and open Web in my estimations would leave the world better off, assuming we could actually get it to take off from the ground, achieving a tangible level of success in terms of users and community support.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Use Technology Creatively</title>
    <link href="https://rseeber.github.io/blog/post/use-technology-creatively/" />
    <updated>2025-08-11T02:25:17Z</updated>
    <id>https://rseeber.github.io/blog/post/use-technology-creatively/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;July 16, 2025&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Email is magic&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good email client is like magic. As technologists, it&#39;s easy to lean into the world of the terminal and operating system, messing around with our Linux installations, Desktop Environments, or other things. It&#39;s easy to lean into this world and see this part as the &amp;quot;real world of computing&amp;quot;, and then look at many of the more business and corporate tools such as email and Office Suites (like Microsoft Office or LibreOffice) as the boring technology, stripped of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, look at your email inbox that you&#39;re forced to use for every service you sign up for. It&#39;s littered with corporate newsletters you didn&#39;t sign up for, advertisements from companies you don&#39;t even have an account with, and political updates from politicians who you thoughts you would care about when you signed up, but you&#39;ve received over 25 messages in a row so far that have remained unread. (Well, that&#39;s my experience anyways).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s easy to look at this and simply blame the corporate style of technology. But email isn&#39;t actually a bad technology, it&#39;s just that most people don&#39;t realize how good it can be if you simply take a few small proactive steps to improve your experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Manage Your Subscriptions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step number one to gain control is to manage how many new messages are coming in to your inbox. My preferred method for this is to maintain two email accounts. The first account you identify as &lt;em&gt;your email account&lt;/em&gt;. It&#39;s the email you list on your website, and it&#39;s the one you give to contacts. You also will give it to any services for which you &lt;em&gt;actively want to recieve updates from&lt;/em&gt;. Not weird marketing emails from a service you don&#39;t care to use for more than a week after signing up. Not sales ads from an online store you bought one thing from 2 months ago. Updates that you specifically, intentionally thought to yourself, &amp;quot;yeah, I think I want to get emails from these people, that would enrich my life or help me out in some way.&amp;quot; For the other services, the ones that send you junk mail you don&#39;t care for, but which you still need an email to sign up with, you sign up through your second email. This inbox does not get checked unless they tell you to check it for something like a 2FA code or a password reset or something like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority of services you use shouldn&#39;t get access to your &amp;quot;real&amp;quot; inbox, they get access to the secondary one. The one you don&#39;t check. This reduces the amount of messages you get in your first inbox, allowing you to actually read those few numbers of emails that actually &lt;em&gt;do matter&lt;/em&gt;. It also means you can confidently hand your email out to contacts and not get stressed out to the prospect of having to check it once in a while so that you don&#39;t miss their message. Herman from Bearblogs mentions something along the lines of this strategy in his post about digital hygiene.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://herman.bearblog.dev/digital-hygiene-emails/&quot;&gt;https://herman.bearblog.dev/digital-hygiene-emails/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This method can be further enhanced by using email filters to automatically sort emails into different folders of your inbox, though I personally don&#39;t receive enough emails in my &amp;quot;real&amp;quot; inbox to warrant that level of organization. The 4 emails a week I get are easy enough to handle without the extra tooling. That may change if I begin receiving more emails from contacts and real humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;It&#39;s Not Just Email&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fixing your email is a great move, it means you don&#39;t miss things. You come off to others as a more put together person. It reduces stress personally from your life. And the fact that it&#39;s such a simple move really is a major selling point on this idea. You don&#39;t need to do anything drastic, just make a new email (or clean up an existing one, unsubscribing from a few emails you&#39;re currently getting on it), and maybe apply some inbox filters if you plan on getting a lot of important messages. This idea is great, and it has a lot of room for further application. We can use the full potential of computing to become more efficient in as many ways as we feel creative, inspired, and compelled to explore. I&#39;d like to detail some of these other tricks you can use. All of these are going to be 1) simple and 2) offer non-negligible payouts for minimal effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Text Documents&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a folder on your computer, just for general working notes is really important to me. I think anyone who works on a computer should have such a thing. Inside of it, you can include all kinds of things. There&#39;s of course your general todo lists (I do my day-to-day lists analog, keeping only big picture stuff digital), but then there&#39;s all the notes you need for remembering small details on a project you&#39;re handling, or for creative thinking while working through a fuzzy problem, or for keeping track of changing details regarding something as time goes by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally advocate for using them as simple text files, using .txt or .md extensions. You don&#39;t need to use a Word Document file to do this. Text files are easy to open -- virtually any program will accept them -- and they don&#39;t obscure anything. Their pure simplicity is a factor of freedom, not constraint. The fact that it&#39;s just text, often rendered in a monospace font, means you are given a free canvas with which to format and organize your document. The simplicity is the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t want to use a raw text file, don&#39;t. But if you&#39;re like me, and are comfortable editing files from raw text editors like vim, or on other operating systems, Notepad, I recommend doing it this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(As a side note, if you happen to be looking for a better way to keep all of your endless notes organized, I recommend giving VimWiki a look. It&#39;s an easy to install extension for Vim, the terminal-based text editor. It allows you to put hyperlinks into your text documents that point to one another. It&#39;s also got a lot of quality of life features that are great, but I don&#39;t want to derail too far by going into depth about it. I&#39;ll let you look into it yourself.)
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://vkc.sh/vimwiki-101/&quot;&gt;https://vkc.sh/vimwiki-101/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://tinkerbetter.tube/w/6hrXmYYNMjBGJnSE8iJ6NM&quot;&gt;https://tinkerbetter.tube/w/6hrXmYYNMjBGJnSE8iJ6NM&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimwiki.github.io/&quot;&gt;https://vimwiki.github.io/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of these files is incredible. Not just for writing simple notes, but you can generate detailed logs which will be useful to you as a reference guide. Take, for instance, the idea of a Suspense File. This list is used in order to track not your own progress, but to track things you&#39;re waiting on others to do. It&#39;s not designed to track them in some controlling, &amp;quot;hurry up and stop making me wait&amp;quot; kind of way. It&#39;s more like &amp;quot;oh wow, me and Rachel were talking about doing xyz, but it&#39;s been 2 weeks since any news from her. She&#39;s probably too busy to make it all work out in time. Let&#39;s take a look. If she&#39;s making progress, it would be good to know about it, and if not, I&#39;ll give her an out and let her off the hook if she needs it.&amp;quot; The idea is that people are busy, and the natural tendencies of people working together on a stagnant project is to just let it silently fall through. The point of the suspense file is to make sure if it does fall through, it&#39;s because you identified that one of you lacked in the time or resources necessary to make it work, and explicitly communicated that you wanted to drop the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That tends to be the more useful aspect of using lists. Lists don&#39;t help you know what to do, they help you decide what you &lt;em&gt;aren&#39;t&lt;/em&gt; going to do. Which projects you don&#39;t have time for, and need to ditch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The suspense file works like this. Each line is a new entry. You can organize it however you like, but this is the method I use, and it&#39;s the one Cory Doctorow describes, which is where I learned of the concept in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each line starts with &amp;quot;&lt;code&gt;WAITING&lt;/code&gt;&amp;quot;, followed the category. After that, you describe who you&#39;re waiting on, and for what specifically. Finally, add a trailing string of dates for whenever a new development is made. If you communicate back and forth with someone for 3 weeks on a project, you might see over a dozen dates appended to the end of this line. The idea is that it gives you an idea of how long you&#39;ve been trying to get the ball rolling on something, and how many interactions have taken place so far.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://pluralistic.net/2024/10/26/one-weird-trick/&quot;&gt;https://pluralistic.net/2024/10/26/one-weird-trick/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example (fake) entry might look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  &lt;code&gt;WAITING Email from Prof. J on CS Club availability for advisorship 2/12, 2/16, 2/20&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 3 separate interactions about it, I might decide that she&#39;s too busy and start looking into other options. On the other hand, she might have just been temporarily bogged down, but will be free again starting next week, and that fact just needs to be communicated. Either way, it helps me identify the progress or stagnation of a plan, and easily track whether I need to reach out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the point isn&#39;t to control anyone, or be an incessant nag (that would be weird). The point is to identify which projects are lagging behind secretly without being noticed, so I can communicate with others involved, and see if this is something that can be remedied somehow, or if we need to drop the project in pursuit of other aims that are demanding more of our time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Keeping Up With Updates&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our age of information overload, where we are often expected to stay up to date with a number of ever changing events at 400 words a second, it can be helpful to institute some simple practices that greatly help us to manage all that information we&#39;re expected to take in regularly. We want both to be able to quickly have access to that information without too much mental strain on actually &lt;em&gt;trying to find it&lt;/em&gt;, as well as wanting a system in place that allows us to know which information sources we &lt;em&gt;still haven&#39;t looked at yet&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is simple, we want some database of all our sources like blogs, news sites, product updates, etc in a singular place where we can quickly check all of them. The second goal is a little more nuanced. Perhaps we spent the first 15 minutes of the day checking through our updates, but get cut off before checking the last one. Or, for instance, perhaps we&#39;re following a large number of publication sources, but each source only puts out a small number of articles per month. Many times we check, there will be nothing new. It would be worth having a kind of system that keeps track of which source has received updates lately, and which ones we don&#39;t need to bother checking in on yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucky for us, a tool for this already exists that covers both of our needs at once. It&#39;s called RSS feeds (or sometimes &amp;quot;Atom feeds&amp;quot;. I think there&#39;s a nuanced difference between them, but from the perspective of a user, they function exactly the same). You can follow the RSS feed of a publication source online, such as a blog or many news sites. You will store these feed links into an application called an RSS Reader. There&#39;s a lot of apps to choose from, but I personally like to use Mozilla Thunderbird for it. That way, it&#39;s stored in a folder right next to my emails inside of the same program. You can use something else if you like, there&#39;s plenty of options to choose from if you just care to do a quick search online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you subscribe to a particular feed through your app, it shows up as a little folder of updates. When you click on the folder, it shows you any recent posts from that source. Unread posts are highlighted a different color so you know you haven&#39;t seen them yet. You can read the title of each post and decide if it&#39;s worth your time or not. I&#39;m currently following over a dozen feeds, though checking through them often only takes a little bit of time each day. Some days, I use it to keep up with light, enjoyable reading from popular posts on the Bearblogs blogging platform.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://bearblog.dev/discover/&quot;&gt;https://bearblog.dev/discover/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also use it to keep up with the news, dev updates relating to Arch Linux, or other projects I&#39;m following, podcasts I listen to, and noteworthy blogs I follow outside of the Bearblogs trending page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most sites that post regular articles will have an RSS feed you can follow somewhere. Heck, even YouTube provides one for each channel, even if they don&#39;t necessarily advertise about it, or make it easy to find. I use an online tool to convert channel links into RSS feeds.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://ytrss.pesky.moe/&quot;&gt;https://ytrss.pesky.moe/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Without RSS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t have an RSS feed for a site, you get two options. Either don&#39;t follow their updates, or find a way to follow it anyways. An easy way to do the second option is to create a basic &amp;quot;startup&amp;quot; bookmarks folder in your web browser. Every time you check your RSS feeds, you&#39;ll also open that startup folder, comb through if anything demands your attention, closing each tab once you&#39;re finished. This should take usually take a few minutes each day, unless you&#39;re putting a bunch of news sources into this folder, which I would not recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also use these folders to check up on special pages that require you to log in to your account to view. If you&#39;re trying to follow the shipping on a particular product you&#39;ve purchased, or check if some important lab result from your hospital has been posted to your account yet, rather than stressing about it, you can just right click your folder and &amp;quot;Open All Bookmarks&amp;quot;. Comb through if an update has been posted, and be done in less than 5 minutes. Once you&#39;ve received the update you were waiting on, you can delete the bookmark if you no longer need to check it regularly. You can always add it back again later if you get more labs done, or buy another product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is that each of these tricks are &lt;em&gt;dead simple&lt;/em&gt;. They each provide moderate to high payouts for realistically small effort required to institute them. They utilize the power of computing to solve problems that computers are uniquely capable of solving efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article has largely been inspired by the general principles laid out in Cory Doctorow&#39;s post on Suspense Files (linked above), as well as his Lifehacking liveblog he links to at the beginning of that post. The idea that people who are keen with technology can use that technology in ways beyond just what everyone else is already doing (often without much thinking on the matter). To actually think critically about the tools at your disposal and find clever ways to use them that makes you accomplish more, it&#39;s a simple idea but it&#39;s also incredibly powerful.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://craphound.com/lifehacksetcon04.txt&quot;&gt;https://craphound.com/lifehacksetcon04.txt&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m only really just starting down the path of experimenting with and discovering creative ideas like the ones I&#39;ve laid out in this post. If you&#39;ve got any of your own that I didn&#39;t mention and you think I&#39;d like it, I&#39;d be happy to hear from you. You can feel free to shoot me an &lt;a href=&quot;https://rseeber.github.io/about.html&quot;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt; telling me all about it. I love getting emails from real people -- it&#39;s the explicit reason that I ever went about cleaning my inbox in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Get Off Social Media, Embrace The Web</title>
    <link href="https://rseeber.github.io/blog/post/embrace-the-web/" />
    <updated>2025-08-11T02:25:14Z</updated>
    <id>https://rseeber.github.io/blog/post/embrace-the-web/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;July 27, 2025&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of people right now feel inundated by information. In our digital age, it&#39;s like everything is flying at us all at once, and we&#39;re always just trying to sip from this super-powered firehouse of information. This is largely the fault of social media. Some people today, especially those of us in our 20s, are looking for an escape from this. People are trying to get away from social media, but we don&#39;t want to stop connecting with our friends. We all know that the internet is a great thing! We just want to get away from some of the ills presented by the usage of social media (which is just one of &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; ways to use the internet).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people will have many different strategies for doing this, but in this blog, I&#39;ll be presenting a kind of guide for how to use the World Wide Web as a replacement technology -- a new (old) way to stay online, without having to conform to the limiting format of a centralized service like Facebook or Instagram.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Why The Web?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point of the internet is to facilitate the mass spread of information, without necessarily always needing to go through traditional publishers or gatekeepers. Anyone with an idea can spread it. But when all of that information goes through the bottleneck of a small collection of major platforms -- platforms that can control what is and isn&#39;t allowed -- doesn&#39;t it seem that we&#39;ve lost the point of it all?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even if you&#39;re not going at it for publishing subversive ideas or something like that, the web is still better than our existing social media platforms. The web is an open format. The web is less conducive to mindless consumption. The web encourages more intentional use. Every post you see is because you clicked a link and went there. Content exploration is also easier. You get recommended things online by people who share links to them. Those links post to external sites, not just more content hosted on the same service. There&#39;s no monolithic algorithms over-analyzing your decisions and coming up with recommendations that show up on your &amp;quot;feed&amp;quot;. You have to explore. This already weeds out a lot of the more negative elements of social media, since it requires you to put thought into what you do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It leads to less negativity from people in the comments, and less anxiety created by impulsive scrolling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But all of this requires there to be a community on the web. A community of people who put their things on the web instead of social media, and who offer out links to interesting things they found recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&#39;s begin, how do we get on the web, and what can we do once we&#39;re there?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Getting on the web&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easiest method for getting on the web is to just sign up for a blog. You don&#39;t really have to make it function like a traditional blog though. Blogs are just websites that don&#39;t require you to learn HTML in order to create. You don&#39;t need to be writing entire articles and essays on here. You can just use it as an easy way to have a webpage and make social posts about yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Instagram, perhaps you might have posted a dozen pictures you took when you went to an event, with a one or two sentence long caption underneath. You could do the same thing here. Post your images, and include some text at the bottom (read ahead for how to embed your images if your blog provider doesn&#39;t host them for you). But you&#39;re also free to expand from this if you like. You&#39;re no longer creating something for a bored, apathetic audience with a low attention-span, who will ultimately be looking at your post through an algorithmic feed of junk. On the web, the people looking at your posts are likely to have longer attention-spans. If you wanted to write a whole paragraph or two about your experience, you&#39;d be free to do so, without feeling as though people will scroll past and not read what you&#39;re trying to express.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, you can use a blog, or the web in general, as a way to post the same type of thing you would normally post on social media. The benefit, however, is that you don&#39;t have to cater to the low-attention span that social media creates in people while they&#39;re using it. When you&#39;re on your computer browsing the web, you&#39;re often willing to spend more time looking at a single post than you would be if you were scrolling your phone while bored in line, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let&#39;s get into the more specific guide of &lt;em&gt;how to actually do it&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Guide&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Blog&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First thing&#39;s first, you need to sign up for a blog service. There&#39;s a lot of options out there of course. Honestly, if you wanted, you could even just run a blog by making your own website, but doing all that isn&#39;t necessary. My personal recommendation is to sign up with Bear Blog. They&#39;re great. It&#39;s a small, independent blogging service. They&#39;re simple, but offer plenty of customization. And the whole thing is entirely free. There&#39;s a paid tier that unlocks some extra stuff, but all of the core features you expect from a blog are available without needing to pay for anything.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://bearblog.dev/&quot;&gt;https://bearblog.dev/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyways, you&#39;re going to sign up with something. If you&#39;d prefer a bigger name, you can use something like Substack, Medium, Blogger, or anything else. All these services offer more less the same thing -- a place online that belongs to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might also go ahead and pick a theme for your blog, or even make a custom one yourself, but that&#39;s not strictly necessary, it&#39;s just nice is all. Some blogging services have a few pre-built themes you can just click and apply to your page, which makes things a lot easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hosting Images&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a certain point, you might get the idea that you want to post some images. This is where we&#39;ll need to invoke the use of another service, since most blogs limit the amount of images that they&#39;ll host for you. We&#39;ll want to find a service that hosts images that can be referenced with a permalink to the image file. The best option I&#39;m aware of for this is Imgur, although alternatives definitely exist. We can make an account on Imgur, upload our images, then right click &amp;quot;open image in new tab&amp;quot; and copy the image URL.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://imgur.com/&quot;&gt;https://imgur.com/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This URL is what we will use to embed it into our blog post. This way, the reader can see the image without having to click on any link. If you&#39;re using a service that uses a markdown format, you can embed an image like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  &lt;code&gt;![Image description](image url)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where you replace &#39;image URL&#39; with the URL that you copied, and ideally also fill in an actual description as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re using a visual editor for your blog, you&#39;ll have to dig around for yourself for any image embed buttons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Examples&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so you&#39;ve seen the guide, but now you wanna see what the final product should look like in action. I&#39;ve included two examples. The first is a blog designed by me. You can notice how I&#39;m not trying to be professional or sound like an essayist or anything. I&#39;m just writing like as if this were Twitter or Mastodon or something. There&#39;s no reason to try to be super polished about things unless that&#39;s what you wanna do. You have to think about this in the same way you would think about social media. Do you feel the need for everything on Instagram to be high fidelity content? If not, why should you feel any differently about a blog where you more less post the same type of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second example was done by my friend Trezha, who worked on this idea with me of how the web can be used as a better way to connect online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Post-Roadtrip Thoughts&amp;quot; (by me)
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://riverpunk.bearblog.dev/post-roadtrip-thoughts/&quot;&gt;https://riverpunk.bearblog.dev/post-roadtrip-thoughts/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I went to a Concert&amp;quot; (by Trezha):
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://myfirst.bearblog.dev/i-went-to-a-concert/&quot;&gt;https://myfirst.bearblog.dev/i-went-to-a-concert/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Closing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web is an amazing tool that allows for personal creative expression, and enables us to share those expressions with our friends. It&#39;s a tool that should connect us together. I find that social media doesn&#39;t always promote meaningful connection, and a lot of people my age seem to agree with me. We feel that there are better potential ways to connect with one another than just through the walled garden of social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you&#39;ll consider creating a space for yourself on the free and open web, as opposed to the locked up platforms of Instagram, Facebook, Twitter, or otherwise. You don&#39;t have to leave your social media accounts if you get on the web, you can have both if you like. I just feel that society would be better off if more people felt free to create and post things on the web, and so that content could become linked together. We would develop longer attention spans, the things we post would become more meaningful (even if the content itself didn&#39;t change much), and people would be free to view it without needing to sign up through an authoritarian tech platform that values money over people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article, as well as mine and Trezha&#39;s example posts, were made as part of our team&#39;s submission for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://csgirlies.devpost.com/&quot;&gt;CS Girlies Hackathon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How I use VimWiki for note taking</title>
    <link href="https://rseeber.github.io/blog/post/how-i-use-vimwiki-for-note-taking/" />
    <updated>2025-08-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://rseeber.github.io/blog/post/how-i-use-vimwiki-for-note-taking/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;August 10, 2025&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made an earlier post where I tried my best to inspire folks to use simple tech solutions in strategically useful ways in order to get large gains out of the tech they already have. Among one of the things I discussed was the power of using simple text files to keep track of things. I&#39;d like to expand on that point here and give some of my own technical details of what I use. Of course, any old text editor will work for the job. I&#39;m going above and beyond so I can have extra features and efficiency.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://rseeber.github.io/blog/post/use-technology-creatively/&quot;&gt;https://rseeber.github.io/blog/post/use-technology-creatively/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;VimWiki&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we&#39;re going to be using VimWiki. It&#39;s an extension for the terminal-based text editor vim. First, install vim. After that, the README for the VimWiki project tells you to simply git clone the project into a plugins folder, and run a special command to generate the help pages. It&#39;s all just copy paste into the terminal, super easy stuff.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/vimwiki/vimwiki?tab=readme-ov-file#installation&quot;&gt;https://github.com/vimwiki/vimwiki?tab=readme-ov-file#installation&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Veronica Explains did a pretty good blog post and video tutorial about using VimWiki, which you can take a look at if the official documentation isn&#39;t enough for you. My post is mostly going to be about what you can &lt;em&gt;do with it&lt;/em&gt;, not necessarily a tutorial on the details.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://vkc.sh/vimwiki-101/&quot;&gt;https://vkc.sh/vimwiki-101/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RmEtH5FQs28&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RmEtH5FQs28&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Using it&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so now you&#39;ve got it installed. Open vim, and type &amp;quot;&lt;code&gt;&#92;ww&lt;/code&gt;&amp;quot; to enter VimWiki. It will create a folder in your home directory called &lt;code&gt;~/vimwiki/&lt;/code&gt; where all files will go by default. VimWiki is basically just vim with internal hyperlinks to other text files on your computer. When you create a link to a file and open it, it will automatically &lt;em&gt;create&lt;/em&gt; the file, if it doesn&#39;t already exist. You never need to leave the editor in order to add new files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can of course use nested directories for different types of notes. For instance, you might use &lt;code&gt;~/vimwiki/blog/&lt;/code&gt; for writing up your blog posts, and &lt;code&gt;~/vimwiki/daily/&lt;/code&gt; for all the notes you need at the beginning of your day. That kind of thing. All links are relative, so if you add an index page to &lt;code&gt;~/vimwiki/blog/&lt;/code&gt;, you can refer to all posts as simply their filename without the full path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How I use it&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A natural hierarchical order comes out of this system. You can begin at the top level index page, which lists sub-pages of different categories. Each sub-page lists either actual pages, or even more detailed categories, until finally you dig all the way down to a file where you&#39;re actually writing in, not just listing links. The hierarchy is saved entirely in your &lt;code&gt;~/vimwiki/&lt;/code&gt; folder. It&#39;s all just files and folders. So if you ever want to switch to a different management system and ditch vimwiki, there&#39;s no conversion tool needed, everything is already is an easily readable format. There&#39;s no special vimwiki-specific metadata or databases or anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a few big category pages, including &amp;quot;Journals&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Writing&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Blog&amp;quot;, and some for different projects I&#39;m working on, like school clubs or things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use the journals folder to keep all my generic notes. There&#39;s your typical examples of just brief ideas or little details I need to record for later, but I also like to keep links to or names of media I&#39;ve enjoyed, or that I plan to take a look at later when I have time. I also keep a todo list and a suspense file.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://pluralistic.net/2024/10/26/one-weird-trick/&quot;&gt;https://pluralistic.net/2024/10/26/one-weird-trick/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Blog posts + static site generator&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I also have the blog folder. This site is self-run using a static site hosting service (GitHub pages currently), and I use the static site generator eleventy to turn my markdown files into html pages based on the template for the site. All I do is install the node package into &lt;code&gt;~/vimwiki/blog/&lt;/code&gt; and have it generate my site whenever I finish a new post. I&#39;ve got it configured to output files to a custom directory where I keep the git repo for the website. So when I run the command, it updates my website repo. When I like how it looks, I commit and push the changes, and they become public within a few moments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just for convenience sake, I also keep a &lt;code&gt;~/vimwiki/blog/drafts/&lt;/code&gt; folder which I&#39;ve instructed eleventy to ignore. Once I finish writing a draft, I move it into the parent folder where it can be seen by eleventy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you&#39;ll probably want to configure your VimWiki to use markdown files if you&#39;re doing this, rather than it&#39;s default &lt;code&gt;.wiki&lt;/code&gt; files, which I&#39;m unaware as to whether eleventy can support, but I would assume markdown has better support in any case. You also don&#39;t necessarily need to use eleventy -- any static site generator that is comfortable for you will do.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.11ty.dev/&quot;&gt;https://www.11ty.dev/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea to this whole system is that all your external tools for memory are stored into a singular place. Rather than having to think about where you keep movie suggestions, read later list, todo lists, favorite quotes, and notes on different projects, you can just know that everything is in your VimWiki folder. Just start following links down your category until you land on what you&#39;re looking for. It eases the friction for getting started on a task, and it also makes it easier to transition from one task to another, since your notes are going to be all stored in the same place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Cloud sync + mobile access&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, this is getting into perhaps the more technical, but still doable. You can actually sync your entire &lt;code&gt;~/vimwiki/&lt;/code&gt; folder to the so-called &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;cloud&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; using git. Initialize the repo, and commit all changes. Pick a server you want to use for syncing. I use GitHub because it&#39;s what I know, but some may prefer to use GitLab, or even a VPS or something like that if you&#39;re hoping for some privacy from Big Tech services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, simply set up a &lt;em&gt;private&lt;/em&gt; git repo and push your changes. You&#39;ll need to of course authenticate first to prove you&#39;re allowed access, but after that it should all work. You want it to be this way so that nobody can read your notes or drafts unless they have access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to access it from somewhere else, simply git clone the folder to a separate device, edit the files, then commit and push. The benefit of using simple text files instead of more advanced files like Word Documents is that you can edit them from basically any device, even a phone. A lot of file managers for your phone will come with a text editor pre-installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get even fancier than that though. If you have an Android, you can install a terminal emulator like Termux, which enables you to install packages such as git and vim on your phone. That&#39;s what I do, I git pull my vimwiki folder to get the latest version, and then I open it with vim. I even have the VimWiki plugin installed on it too. I make my edits, then commit and push back up. Of course, that&#39;s not your only option. All you need is a way to push and pull a git repo to your phone, and some kind of generic text editor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Closing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really enjoy my experience with VimWiki, creating a hierarchical note system. I try not to get carried away with the data structure of it all, instead focusing on just keeping notes on important stuff. If you have any other tricks how to make the most out of this tool, feel free to let me know about it! I love endlessly tweaking with my workflow on my laptop to optimize efficiency (or often just coolness factor).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>